"Stay away from me.
Let go."
"Let go of me."
- "Save the phony tears."
- "Just get back."
- "Oh, you little fool."
- "You just stay away from me."
"We can't get involved in this."
Hello, Patrick.
How are you?
Good.
- So what do you think?
- Oh, it's a classic.
You know, it just gets better
and better every time.
Yes.
What do you think
of my request?
I don't think much of it
really, Patrick.
Really, I don't.
Meaning you can't accomplish it?
Any task can be accomplished
as long as it's broken down
into manageable pieces.
So you'll do it?
Look, I know
that I'm in your debt.
Okay, so we both agree
that you owe me a favor.
Yes, I do.
So let this be
my favor to you...
let it go... the whole idea.
It's just not worth it.
Well, I find this very interesting.
I'm presenting you
with a challenge
and yet you're backing away.
It's very unlike you, Mr. Stiles.
Look, if you must know
I've grown mildly accustomed
to you, Patrick.
You make me sit up
and pay attention.
I'm very glad
you're amused by me.
But what you're planning now, it's...
- Well, it's certainly different.
- Yes, it is.
If I do what you're asking
of me and you get caught
you're gonna spend
the rest of your life in a federal prison.
I'm well aware of that.
I just have to make sure
I don't get caught.
All right.
Well, it's been a great pleasure
knowing you, Mr. Jane.
Good luck.
"Well, I... I used
some pretty harsh words."
"I'm sorry."
Thank you.
"But naturally, if I'd known..."
Lorelei Martins, 5474B.
Need a ride?
You?
Hey, come on. Please.
Just... just get in the car.
This is ridiculous.
Why are you mad at me?
I... I didn't force you
to escape from prison.
No, you just tricked me
into it.
Oh, come on.
Wait.
You thought it was Red John
that got you out, didn't you?
Yeah.
Yeah, well, it wasn't.
I did. I got you out.
He would have left you
in there to rot.
And I took a lot of risks
in doing it.
Nobody ever accused you
of good judgment.
Well, what about you? You're the one
walking off into the desert
ten miles from a prison
you just broke out of.
I'm offering you a ride.
I'll take you
wherever you wanna go.
You can dump me at any time.
Fine.
Jane, how many messages
do I have to leave you?
Call me back.
Hold on, Tom.
She just walked in.
No.
No, don't inform
the Marshals yet.
I wanna bring CBI
up to speed first.
I'll call you back.
What's going on?
Have you heard
about Lorelei Martins yet?
No.
She escaped from federal prison
this morning.
Your Mr. Jane was questioning
prison transport drivers.
Yes, but no.
He wouldn't.
He wouldn't?
Where is he now?
I don't know. I haven't heard
from him since yesterday.
He hasn't answered his phone.
But that doesn't mean
he did this.
It would make it
much more likely, wouldn't it?
Why is this
a Homeland Security issue?
It's complicated.
I mean, if he is with her
he's in a lot of danger.
You know him
better than anybody.
Now if he did do this
where would he go?
Any place I could possibly think
of is where he wouldn't go.
Uh, would you excuse me
for a minute?
I'll be right back.
Has anyone seen Jane?
- No.
- We need to find him right now.
Put a B.O.L.O. out on his car. Grace, Cho,
I want you to go to his motel room.
Rigs, call his cell phone company.
Get GPS tracking on his phone.
What's going on?
Lorelei Martins escaped
from prison this morning.
Was Jane involved?
We don't know yet.
Who's that?
Bob Kirkland
Homeland Security.
He's leading the search
to find Martins.
Boss.
Sac PD got a report
of an abandoned blue Citroen this morning.
Uh, parking lot at 16th and K Street.
Text it to me.
This isn't gonna work.
Well, that's optimistic.
I won't tell you
who he is, or where he is.
- Give it time.
- Not now. Not ever.
Doesn't work.
Really?
I figured that when
no sound came out of it.
Yes.
Can we go?
Tell me where.
The ocean.
I wanna see the ocean.
He was leaving a text message.
It's for you.
"Someone after me."
He was being followed.
Looks like he's been abducted.
Jane doesn't have Lorelei.
Lorelei has Jane.
Our fugitive is a known associate
of the serial killer Red John.
She's wanted for murder conspiracy
kidnapping, and weapons violations.
We believe that Martins
and unknown accomplices
abducted CBI consultant
Patrick Jane.
Jane led a six-month
undercover operation
that resulted in Lorelei's arrest.
Martins may have kidnapped him for payback
or to take him to Red John.
Either way
we need to find them.
Martins is a Sacramento girl.
I want systematic searches
of old residences
old friends, old coworkers.
You all have information packets.
Study them, and when you're done
contact myself or Agent Kirkland
for your assignments.
Thank you.
- Let's start with Lorelei's mother.
- Okay.
I wonder where they're going.
I'm gonna make a fire.
So, what's this about?
Your daughter broke out of prison
this morning.
Oh, great. Of course.
Have you had any contact
with... with Lorelei recently?
Lorelei hasn't contacted me in years.
Thankfully.
When she does...
it's always trouble. Always.
We have reason to believe
that Lorelei has taken a hostage.
His life could be in danger.
Do you have any information
that you could give us
about where we could find her?
Any, uh, old friends?
Favorite places?
Nope. I don't have
anything to do with her
and she doesn't have
anything to do with me.
Do you have any insight
as to how she became this way?
Lorelei only ever cared about Lorelei.
What are you gonna do
with a kid like that?
Well, you don't feel
at all responsible for her?
Now there's a question
from a woman without children.
I've satisfied all my duties
and responsibilities of motherhood.
I mean, look around. Lorelei
grew up in a beautiful home.
She could be anything.
Is this your father?
That's my husband.
He's away in Munich.
He's away a lot?
Yes.
Oh. Figures.
I don't like your tone.
Dana, your daughter
is the mistress of a psychopathic killer
yet you have no information to give us
about how or why
she got that way.
Frankly, I don't care
if you like my tone.
To hell with you, lady.
What happened to her?
Get out of my house!
Thank you.
You should try it.
Water's lovely.
Uh, quickly... go and hide
yourself behind those rocks.
Hello, young man.
How you doing?
Was that your campfire?
No, Officer.
I'm not an officer.
I'm a Park Ranger.
So no gun, huh?
Right.
Campfires are illegal
on this beach without a permit.
It's not mine.
Are you okay, sir?
You seem a little nervous.
Never better.
Are you alone?
Uh... No, she's...
Hi, Officer!
I'm over here!
I'm sorry. I can't come out!
I don't have any clothes on.
Yeah, well, public nudity's
prohibited on state beaches.
Yes, uh, I'm sorry!
It won't happen again!
Promise, it...
it won't happen again.
Sorry, sir.
Okay.
You folks have a nice day.
Yeah.
No campfires.
So where to now?
North to Canada?
South to Mexico?
I'm flexible.
I know a place
where no one will find us.
Take the I-60 East, but I
gotta change my look first.
Find a convenience store.
- I like the take-charge attitude.
- No, you don't.
I do.
Clearly, you've taken care
of someone in your life.
Made all the decisions.
Acted the adult.
I'm guessing you had a vain, selfish
and controlling mother.
But you found
the strength to pull away.
Does she resent you for that?
Patrick, do you really
wanna get to know me?
Of course.
Give the act a rest.
- What? I... I wasn't...
- Yes, you were.
Okay.
"I knew it."
Soon as I heard that kidnapping
report on my radio.
I called it in.
This is the young man
I talked to.
- Was there a woman with him?
- Yes, there most certainly was.
Only I didn't see her
on account of she was naked.
At least that what she said.
She was behind that rock there
where she was changing.
The young man got kind of jumpy.
Uh-huh.
Asked me if I had a gun.
She probably had a gun
on you the whole time.
That's what I figured.
And if he said one wrong word
or tried to run... bam.
I mean, she would have
shot us both dead.
I'm just thankful he kept his head.
Happen to see what kind
of car they were driving?
Yes, sir. There was
only one car on the bluff.
A dark blue 1990s Dynasty Sedan.
Stay low.
Thank you.
Put these... Put these up there.
Scared you, didn't I?
No.
Saw some cops. Spooked me.
Well, I'm glad I left you the keys.
You're gonna be
a French honey blonde.
- How's that sound?
- Sure.
- Did you get snacks?
- Sure did.
I have something to say.
Come in. Sit down, Dana.
What's going on?
Couldn't sleep last night.
Hmm.
My husband mustn't know.
Mustn't know what?
I sold Lorelei's sister.
A sister?
I don't remember reading anything
about a sister in Lorelei's file.
Because I sold her.
All right, you're gonna have
to help me out here, Dana.
Thirty years ago, I didn't have
the money to raise two girls.
I had substance issues.
Go on.
So after...
their dad left...
I just stopped functioning
you know?
And, um, Lorelei...
she was five.
And she held me up, you know?
But...
Miranda...
that was her name...
She was two.
I mean, what was I gonna do
with a two-year-old?
What did you do?
Well, I knew...
I knew this rich... foreign couple
who... childless.
So we made a deal under
the table.
Why didn't they just adopt her?
We all wanted what we wanted
so we just got it done.
What did you tell Lorelei?
I told her...
I told her all kinds of stuff.
I...
And she never forgave me.
I didn't realize it at the time
but... that day...
I lost two daughters.
Not one.
Want me to get you a tissue?
Hurry up!
Hey there.
Looking for a room.
Place to rest my weary bones.
Been on the road
since New Mexico.
- It's $48 cash, $52 credit.
- Oop. I'll be paying cash.
Okay.
You don't happen
to have one without a television?
Uh, TV's busted in 13.
No discount.
Okay.
- Have a nice day.
- Mm-hmm.
We tried to have
our own children.
I could not.
Why didn't you
just adopt legally?
Well, I was on work visa
from Romania.
And we could not adopt
until we were citizens
and that takes years.
Mr. Kirkland
this is Marta and Virgil Roman.
They're just telling me how they
came to buy Miranda Martins.
You had to see her.
She was in a bad situation.
Virgil and I knew we could
give her a life
full of love and opportunity.
But she turned out to be
a very troubled girl.
Very unhappy.
So when she was in high school
we sent her to a therapist
and she remembered
a lot of things
we thought
she had forgotten.
Her mother?
No.
She remembered
only one name.
Lorelei.
Of course, we found
her sister Lorelei
and reunited them.
The sisters were so happy
and they were so close.
You've never seen
two sisters who were closer.
Where is Miranda now?
We need to talk to her.
She... she was murdered.
She's dead.
It's a shame the TV doesn't work.
Thanks for the dress.
Oh, it's my pleasure.
So, listen, uh...
You gonna tell me
where we're going?
To a cabin my sister and I
used to go to.
- You have a sister?
- I did.
I'm sorry.
Don't be.
Her death was a gift, sort of.
- You wanna explain that?
- You wouldn't understand.
Well, you could try me.
I mean, I... I'd like
to understand.
In case you haven't noticed
healing is not my strong suit.
Losing my sister brought me
into my full reality.
I faced my deepest fear.
I have complete awareness.
Nothing can hurt me.
That's nonsense.
Believe me.
Things can hurt you.
Try me.
Mm. This beer is warm.
I'll get some ice.
Miranda was beautiful
like her sister.
What does the coroner's report
say about the cause of death?
Heatstroke.
After she was raped
she was left chained
inside of an empty warehouse.
Daytime temperatures
reached 120 degrees inside.
Coroner figures
she lasted about two days.
And they never found the killer?
The case is still open.
There's no trace evidence
no witnesses.
Just this.
- Hello?
- "Hey, Lisbon."
I need your help.
I need to take this. Could you...
I'll be right back.
"And this refrain was her song"
"Red sails in the sunset"
Jane, what's going on?
Have you been kidnapped?
Yes. I'm in fear of my life.
I can't talk long.
Did you know Lorelei
had a sister?
Yes. Miranda.
Her mother gave her up.
Where are you?
If she catches me on the phone
she'll kill me.
- What happened to Miranda?
- She was murdered.
Abducted, raped, and left
for dead five years ago.
- "Who did it?"
- They don't know.
They don't even have a suspect.
But listen to this...
"The police kept back
a key detail from the public."
Before Miranda died
she carved a message
into the warehouse floor.
What'd it say?
I'm looking at the crime scene
photo now.
It says "Roy".
I need a copy of that photo.
Uh, Lisbon, yeah. Fax it
to me at this number...
"I'm Katie Riley"
"and I'll be back with more
of your favorite mellow blends"
"right after the news."
"State and federal authorities
have intensified the search"
"for a Sacramento woman,
Lorelei Martins."
Jane, just tell me
where you are.
We can help you.
Just fax it to me.
I gotta go. Gotta go.
"According to police, Martins has
kidnapped CBI consultant, Patrick Jane"
"whose car was found abandoned
by the side of the road."
Everything okay?
Jane just called me.
You filthy liar!
Kidnapped you?
Please...
How dare you? You lied!
I didn't lie. I just
didn't tell you everything.
- Why didn't you tell me?
- I had to protect myself.
Ah!
Oh!
Please. Just stop.
You had me going, Patrick.
For a second there
I almost trusted you.
You should.
You should trust me.
Oh, stop!
Just stop playing the role.
Yes, I play a role
but not with you.
- I'm being honest with you.
- Lies on lies!
Lorelei, listen to me.
You have to listen to me.
Your buddy Red John...
he killed your sister.
- What are you talking about?
- Your sister Miranda.
She wrote a name on the floor
of the warehouse where she died.
The name of the man
who raped and killed her.
It was never released
to the public.
- You're making that up.
- No.
This is a crime scene photo
of your sister's murder
- "Roy".
- Yes, Roy.
We both know
who uses that alias.
I don't understand.
- Where did you get this?
- It doesn't matter.
Red John raped
and killed your sister.
- No.
- He made you a victim
so that he could rescue you.
- No.
- He preyed on your pain.
- No, it's not true.
- Yes. You don't want it to be true.
But it's true, and you can
feel that it's true.
Just stop!
God, you're just
like him, you know that?
- Relentless manipulation.
- I am nothing like him.
How would you know?
I know.
I only wonder why the two of you
didn't become lifelong friends
the moment you shook hands.
Wait!
Where are we going?
We still going to the cabin?
That's where I'm going.
You can go where you like.
We traced Jane's call
to a truck stop motel on Route 99
just north of Chico.
- Right here.
- The fugitive and her hostage were gone
by the time
deputies got to the motel.
"They were moving north."
Let's assume they still are.
Where are they going?
Well, if they take the 97 North
they'll hit the Butter Valley Airport.
One runway. Public use.
Five takeoffs a day.
They might go for a plane.
Okay, lock it down. What else?
I've been going through financial records
for Lorelei's sister.
She owned a cabin in the Sierras
about 200 miles north
of that motel.
From what I can see, the cabin
was never sold after her death.
An anonymous third party has
been paying the taxes on it.
Red John?
Call tactical.
I want a chopper here in ten.
It's just up ahead
at the end of the road.
You go ahead.
I'll get the stuff.
Okay.
The key is under the flower pot.
Welcome.
Well, it's a nice place.
Yeah.
Belonged to my sister.
We used to come here
to forget about the world.
It's safe.
Red John didn't kill her, Patrick.
You'll never convince me
that he did.
I'd kill for a cup of tea right now.
I can make you one.
I'd like that.
- But we can't stay here.
- Why not?
If Miranda bought this place
the police will find it.
They're probably
on their way here right now.
- Then we have to go.
- No, you have to go.
- I'll stay. I'll try and delay them.
- What?
Well, like you said
I'm never gonna convince you
that Red John killed your sister.
You need to go and find out
the truth for yourself.
But, Patrick...
And when you do
when you know the truth...
You know where to find me.
Just call me.
Where are the car keys?
In the car.
Is there a back way
out of here?
Um, there's... no.
There's just fire trails.
Okay. What about this thing?
Does this run?
- It's been on a trickle charge.
- Yeah, it should.
Okay, you take the 4x4
on the fire road.
They won't be looking for that.
I'm gonna cover for you.
You can't stay here, Patrick.
There's no way they'll believe
you were my hostage.
I will make them believe.
You want me to beat you up
or something?
- Knock you out?
- Uh, no, thanks.
You gotta go.
Check the cabin.
Search the surrounding woods.
Jane.
He's okay.
Did you get her?
Not yet.
She's, uh, she's on foot.
Agent Kirkland
Homeland Security.
I need rescue hot
south of Orr Lake
forest Route 42 North 12.
- Who's that guy?
- Don't talk.
Help's on the way.
Hurts.
Shh. It's okay.
You'll never know.
I'll never know what?
Whether I engineered
the escape and abduction.
Trust me. I know.
You don't know.
You just guess.
And you didn't tell your new
best friend, Kirkland, either.
I don't have any evidence.
If I did, I'd put you
in cuffs myself.
- No, you wouldn't.
- Try me.
- What's so funny?
- Nothing. Sorry.
All of it's worth it.
She told me Red John and I
are very much alike.
That it's a wonder
we weren't best friends
from the moment
we shook hands.
You've met Red John?
Yes.
He's someone I know.